This section deals with renal tumors. The first tumor that we want to cover is an angiomyolipoma.
Angio means blood vessel, myo means smooth muscle, and lipo means fat.
And so this is a tumor, a hematoma in particular, that's comprised of blood vessel, smooth muscle, and adipose tissue.
The most important thing to know for purposes of board examinations is that this tumor is increased in frequency in patients with tuberous sclerosis.
And that's the high yield for this entity.
Renal cell carcinoma is a malignant epithelial tumor that arises from the kidney tubules.
It classically presents with this triad of hematuria, a palpable mass, and flank pain.
This is the triad that we all memorize when we think about renal cell carcinoma.
But interestingly, all three symptoms rarely occur together.
In fact, in only 10% of patients would you see all three symptoms.
Hematuria is overall the most common presenting symptom.
In addition to this classic triad, patients can also present with fever or weight loss.
Now, one of the very high yield points to note concerning renal cell carcinoma is that it can produce multiple perineoplastic syndromes.
For example, it could release erythropoietin, causing a reactive polycythemia.
It could release renin, causing hypertension.
It can release parathyroid hormone-related peptide, causing hypercalcemia.
Or it can release ACTH, causing Cushing syndrome.
So, it's very important to note that renal cell carcinoma can produce many different perineoplastic syndromes.
Again, that's particularly high yield to bear in mind.
Rarely, renal cell carcinoma can present with a left-sided varicocele.
This is particularly high yield because of its anatomy tie-in.
Let's recall that if this is the inferior vena cava and this is the renal vein here on the left side,
that the spermatic vein drains into the renal vein on the left side.
So, if the kidney is here and renal cell carcinoma occurs,
renal cell carcinoma has a propensity to involve the renal vein.
So, imagine that if it involves the renal vein and blocks the renal vein,
that would block drainage of the spermatic vein, which would then result in a varicocele.
So, this doesn't usually occur on the right side because recall from anatomy that on the right side,
the spermatic vein directly drains into the inferior vena cava.
And so, therefore, even if you had a right-sided renal cell carcinoma invading the renal vein,
this would not block the drainage of the spermatic vein.
Therefore, you don't usually see right-sided varicoceles with renal cell carcinoma.
When renal cell carcinoma occurs, it usually produces a yellow mass.
And, microscopically, the most common histologic variant exhibits clear cytoplasm,
and hence it's called the clear cell type.
Here's a picture of the yellow mass produced by renal cell carcinoma.
Again, this is the normal kidney, and this is the fat or the adipose tissue that surrounds the kidney.
Here's the histology, again, showing you that there is clear cytoplasm in these cells,
and hence the most common subtype of renal cell carcinoma is called clear cell carcinoma.
Very important to note, and particularly high yield, that the pathogenesis of renal cell carcinoma
involves loss of VHL, which is a tumor suppressor gene.
Now, when you lose VHL, that increases insulin-like growth factor, which promotes growth,
and it also increases HIF transcription factor,
which increases both vascular endothelial growth factor and platelet-derived growth factor.
So, that would promote both angiogenesis and growth of the tumor.
Now, there are two classic pathways to develop renal cell carcinoma.
The first is the sporadic pathway, and the second is the hereditary pathway.
In the sporadic pathway, you classically get a single tumor, usually in the upper pole of the kidney,
that arises in an adult smoker.
And so, again, smoking is the key risk factor for the sporadic pathway.
In the hereditary pathway, you classically get tumors that arise in younger patients,
and they're often multiple and bilateral.
Now, again, both the sporadic pathway and the hereditary pathway involve loss of the VHL tumor suppressor gene.
One hereditary syndrome, which can result in renal cell carcinoma, is von Hippolindau disease.
This is an autosomal dominant disorder in which there is inactivation of the VHL gene.
Now, this increases the risk not only for renal cell carcinoma,
but the patients also get hemangioblastoma of the cerebellum in association with renal cell carcinoma.
The staging for renal cell carcinoma is based on tumor size and involvement of the renal vein.
Remember that renal cell carcinoma loves to go to the renal vein,
and this increases the risk of hematogenous spread to both the lungs and the bone.
In addition, renal cell carcinoma can go to lymph node,
and when it goes to lymph node, it classically goes to the retroperitoneal lymph nodes.
Another tumor that can arise in the kidney is called Wilms tumor.
For the purposes of examination as well as clinical practice,
this is the most common tumor that would arise in children.
The average age is three.
So on board exam, if you have a kidney mass in a child,
you're really thinking about Wilms tumor.
Now, this tumor is comprised of blastema.
Blastema is the primitive tissue from which the kidney forms,
and this blastema can also produce primitive glomeruli tubules and some stromal cells.
However, the hallmark cell is blastema.
Here's an image highlighting a Wilms tumor.
All of these small dark blue cells here, they all represent blastema.
Now, you can also see that there's a stromal component,
and focally, there's also formation of a tubule.
However, again, the key component in this tumor is blastema,
and it's the blastema that has the ability to form stroma along with tubules and primitive glomeruli.
Patients with Wilms tumor generally present with a large unilateral flank mass,
classically with both hematuria and hypertension,
and the hypertension is actually due to renin secretion.
Wilms tumor is associated with WT1 mutations, especially in syndromic cases.
One high-yield example of a syndromic case would be the WAGR syndrome.
The W stands for Wilms tumor, the A for aniridia, the G for genital anomalies,
and then the R for mental and motor retardation.
Another syndrome in which we can get Wilms tumor is Beckwith-Williaman syndrome.
Of course, the patients would have Wilms tumor,
but it would be associated with neonatal hypoglycemia,
muscular hemihypertrophy, where the muscles on one half of the body
are bigger than the muscles on the other half,
and organomegaly, especially involving the tongue.
And that concludes this section of renal neoplasia.